<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xml:id="treh0001" n="iip">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <!-- *************************************  <titleStmt>  *********************************
                
            -->
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Inscriptions of Israel/Palestine</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Creator</resp>
                    <name xml:id="MS">Michael Satlow</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <!-- *************************************  <publicationStmt>  *********************************  -->
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Brown University</authority>
                <idno/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <!--  *************************************  <sourceDesc>  ********************************* -->
            <sourceDesc>
                <!--  *************************************  <msDesc>  ********************************* 
                       repeat the id number here. This is an Epidoc convention.
                -->
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <idno type="IIP">Treh 0001</idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <!--  *************************************  <msContents>  ********************************* -->
                    <msContents>
                        <textLang mainLang="he" otherLangs="arc"/>
                        <msItem class="legal" ana="jewish">
                            <p>Tel Rehov, 6-7th century CE. Mosaic. Halakhic regulations.</p>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <!--  *************************************  <physDesc>  ********************************* -->
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc ana="mosaic">
                            <supportDesc ana="stone">
                                <support>
                                    <p/>
                                    <dimensions type="surface" unit="cm">
                                        <height>430</height>
                                        <width>275</width>
                                        <depth/>
                                    </dimensions>
                                </support>
                                <condition ana="fragment.single">
                                    <p/>
                                </condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout columns="1" writtenLines="29">
                                    <p/>
                                </layout>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <!--  *************************************  <handDesc>  *********************************  -->
                        <handDesc>
                            <handNote ana="inset.mosaic">
                                <p/>
                            </handNote>
                        </handDesc>
                        <!--  *************************************  <decoDesc>  *********************************  -->
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote>
                                <ab/>
                                <locus/>
                            </decoNote>
                        </decoDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <summary>
                            <rs/>
                        </summary>
                        <origin><date notBefore="0500" notAfter="0638"
                                period="http://n2t.net/ark:/99152/p0m63njjcn4">500-638 CE</date><placeName>
                                <region>Jordan Valley</region>
                                <settlement ref="https://pleiades.stoa.org/places/678363">Tel
                                    Rehov</settlement>
                                <geogName type="site">Synagogue</geogName>
                                <geogFeat type="locus"/>
                            </placeName>
                            <p/>
                        </origin>
                        <provenance>
                            <placeName/>
                        </provenance>
                    </history>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <!--  *************************************  <encodingDesc>  ********************************
            
            Encoders do not edit the <encodingDesc>.
        -->
        <encodingDesc>
            <xi:include href="http://cds.library.brown.edu/projects/iip/include_taxonomies.xml">
                <xi:fallback>
                    <p>Taxonomies for IIP controlled values</p>
                </xi:fallback>
            </xi:include>
        </encodingDesc>
        <!-- Ignore profileDesc for now -->
        <profileDesc/>
        <!--  *************************************  <revisionDesc>  ********************************* -->
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2022-12-30" who="Chris Zeichmann">Initial Entry</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!--  *************************************  <facsimile>  *********************************    -->
    <facsimile>
        <graphic url=""/>
        <surface>
            <desc>דניאל ונטורה (Wikipedia CC 3.0)</desc>
            <note>https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Ktovet_recov_AA.jpg</note>
            <graphic url="treh0001.jpg"/>
        </surface>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="edition" subtype="diplomatic" ana="b1">
                <p xml:lang="heb"/>
            </div>
            <div type="edition" subtype="transcription" ana="b1">
                <p xml:lang="heb"><unclear>ש</unclear>לום הפירות הללו אסורין בבית שאן בשביעית ובשאר
                    שבוע מתאסרין דמי הקישואין<lb/> והאבטיחין והממלפפונות והאסטפליני
                        והמינת<unclear>ה</unclear> הנאג<unclear>ר</unclear>ת בפני עצמה ופול המצרי
                    הנאגד<lb/> בשיפה והקפלוטות מן העצרת עד החנוכה והזירעונין והקצע והשמשמין והחרדל
                    והאורז והכמן והתורמסין<lb/> היבישין והאפונין הגמלונין הנימכרין במידה והשום
                    ובצלין בני מדינה הנימכרין במידה והבולבסין<lb/> והתמרין אפסיות והיין והשמן
                    בשביעית שביעית שני שבוע דמי והפת חלה לעולם אילו המקומות<lb/> המותרין סביבות בית
                    שאן מן ה<unclear>דר</unclear>ום שהיא פילי דקמפון עד חקלה חיורתה מן המערב<lb/>
                    שהיא פילי דזיירה עד סוף הרצפה מן הצפון שהיא פילי דס<unclear>כ</unclear>ותה עד
                    כפר קרנוס וכפר קרנוס<lb/>
                    <unclear>כ</unclear>בית שאן ומן המיזרח שהיא פילי דזבלייה עד נפשה דפנוקטייה ופילי
                    דכפר <unclear>ז</unclear>מרין ופילי ראגמה<lb/> לפנים מן השער מותר ולחוץ אסור
                    העיירות האסורות ביתחום סוסיתה עינוש ועינ<unclear>ח</unclear>רה ודמבר<lb/>
                        עי<unclear>ון</unclear> ויערוט וכפר יחריב ונוב וח<unclear>ס</unclear>פייה
                    וכפר צמח ורבי היתיר כפר צמח העיירות שהן ספיק בתחום נווה<lb/> ציר וצייר וגשמיי
                    וזיזון ורנב וחרבתה ואיגרי חוטם וכרכה דבר הרג העיירות אסורות בתחום צור שצת<lb/>
                    ובצת ופימצובה וחנותה עלייתה וחנותה ארעייתה וביברה וראש מייה ואמון ומזה היא קסטלה
                        <unclear>ו</unclear>כל מה שקנו ישראל<lb/> נאסר תחומי ארץ ישראל מקום
                        ש<unclear>ה</unclear><supplied reason="lost">חזיקו</supplied> עולי בבל פורשת
                    אשקלון וחומת מיגדל שרושן דור וחומת עכו<lb/> וראש מי גיאתו וגיאתו עצמה
                        וכבר<supplied reason="lost">תה</supplied>
                    <supplied reason="lost">וב</supplied><unclear>י</unclear>ת זניתה וקסטרה רגלילה
                    וקובעייה ראייתה וממצייה דירכתה<lb/> ומלתה דכוריים וסחרתה דיתי<supplied
                        reason="lost">ר</supplied>
                    <supplied reason="lost">ונחל</supplied>ה דבצאל ובית עיט וברשתה ואולי דבתה
                    וניקבתה<lb/> רעיון ומסב ספנחה וכרכה רב<supplied reason="lost">ר</supplied>
                    <supplied reason="lost">ס</supplied>נגורה ותרנגולה עלייה דקיסריון ובית סבל
                    וקנת<lb/> ורקם טרכון זימרה דמתחם לבו<unclear>צר</unclear>ה ינקה זחשבון ונחלח
                    דזרד איגר סהד<unclear>ו</unclear>תה נימרין<lb/> ומל<unclear>ח</unclear> רזיזה
                    רקם דגיאה וגנייה דאשקלון ודרך הגדולה ההולכת למירבר הפירות<lb/> הללו אסורין בפנים
                    בשביעית ובישאר שני שבוע הן מתעסרין דמיי משלם<lb/> האורז והאגוזין והשמשמין ופול
                    המצרי יש אומרין אוף אחוניות הבכירות<lb/> הדי אלו בשביעית שביעית ובשאר שני שבוע
                    הן מתעסרין וריי ואפילו<lb/> מן תר<unclear>נוג</unclear>לה עלייה
                        ולחו<unclear>ץ</unclear> הפירות הללו מתעסרין דמיי בקסרין החיטין והפת<lb/>
                    חלה ל<unclear>ע</unclear>ולם והיין והשמן והתמרין והאורז והכמן הרי אלו מותרין
                    בשביעית בקסרין<lb/> ובישאר שני שבוע הן מתקנין דמיי ויש אוסרין בולבסין הלבנין
                    הבאין<lb/> מהר המלך ועד איכן סביב לקיסרין עד צוורנה ופנדקה דטביתה ועמודה<lb/>
                    ודור וכפר סבה ואם יש מקום שקנו אותו ישראל חוששין לו רבותינו שלום העיירות<lb/>
                        המו<supplied reason="omitted">ת</supplied>דות בתחום סבסטי איקבין וכפר כסדיה
                        ו<unclear>ע</unclear>יר ואזילין ושפירין ועננין ובלעם עלייתה
                        ומ<unclear>ז</unclear>חרו<lb/> ודותן וכפר מייה ושילתה ופנטאקומוותה ולבייה
                    ופרדיסלייה ו<unclear>י</unclear>צת וארבנ<unclear>ו</unclear>רין וכפר<lb/>
                    <unclear>י</unclear>הודית ומונרית ופלגה דשלאף </p>
            </div>
            <div type="translation" ana="b1">
                <p>Shalom. These fruits are forbidden in Beit She'an during the Seventh Year, but
                    during other years of the seven-year cycle they are tithed as demai-produce:
                    cucumbers, watermelons, muskmelons, parsnip (carrots), mint that is bound by
                    itself, black-eyed peas that are bound with rush, wild leeks between Shavuot and
                    Hanukkah, the seed kernels, black cumin, sesame, mustard, rice, cumin, dried
                    lupines, large-sized peas that are sold by measure, garlic, scallions of the
                    city that are sold by measure, grape hyacinths, late-ripening dates, wine,
                    [olive] oil, on the Seventh Year the seventh-year laws apply [to them]; on the
                    [other] years of the seven-year cycle, they are tithed as demai-produce, and [if
                    there was] a loaf of bread, the Dough portion is always [separated from
                    it].<lb/>These are the places that are permitted in the vicinity of Beit She'an:
                    southward, that is to say, [from] the Gate of Ḳumpōn extending as far as the
                    White Field; from the west, that is to say, [from] the Gate of Zayara extending
                    as far as the end of the pavement; from the north, that is to say, the Gate of
                    Sakkūtha extending as far as Kefar Ḳarnos, while Kefar Ḳarnos [itself] is deemed
                    as Beit She'an; and from the east, that is to say, the Gate of the
                    Dung-spreaders extending as far as the monument of Fannuqatiah, while the Gate
                    of Kefar Zimrin and the Gate of the marshland, in those places that are within
                    the gate, [what is grown] is permitted, but beyond [the gate without, what is
                    grown] is prohibited. The towns that are prohibited in the region of Sussitha
                    [are as follows]: 'Ayyanosh, 'Ain-Ḥura, Dambar, 'Ayūn, Ya'arūṭ, Kefar Yaḥrīb,
                    Nob, Ḥisfiyyah, Kefar Ṣemaḥ; now the Rabbi permitted Kefar Ṣemaḥ. The towns that
                    are of a dubious nature in the region of Naveh [are as follows]: Ṣeir, Ṣayyer,
                    Gashmai, Zayzūn, Renab and its ruin, Igorei Ḥoṭem, and the fortified city
                    (kerakh) of the son of Harag.<lb/><lb/>The towns that are prohibited in the
                    region of Tyre [are as follows]: Shaṣat, Beṣet, Pi Maṣūbah, the Upper Ḥanūtha,
                    the Lower Ḥanūtha, Bebarah, Rosh Mayya, 'Ammon, Mazih which is the Castle, and
                    all which an Israelite has bought is prohibited.<lb/>The boundaries of the Land
                    of Israel, [that is to say], the place held by those returning from Babylonia,
                    [are as follows]: The passage of Ashkelon, the wall of Sharoshan Tower [of
                    Caesarea], Dor, the wall of Akko, the source of the spring of Ǧiyāto and Ǧiyāto
                    itself, Kabritha, Beit Zanitha, the Castle of Galilee, Quba'ya of Ayata, Mamṣi’
                    of Yarkhetha, Miltha of Kurayim, Saḥratha of Yatīr, the riverine brook of Baṣāl,
                    Beit 'Ayit, Barashatha, Awali of Battah, the mountain pass of 'Iyyon, Massab
                    Sefanḥa, the walled city of Bar-Sannigora, the Upper Rooster of Caesarion, Beit
                    Sabal, Ḳanat, Reḳam, Trachonitis of Zimra which is in the region of Buṣrah,
                    Yanqah, Ḥeshbon, the brook of Zered, Igor Sahadutha, Nimrin, Melaḥ of Zayzah,
                    Reḳam of Ǧayāh, the Gardens of Ashkelon and the great road that leads into the
                    desert. These are the fruits that are prohibited in Paneas on the
                    sabbatical-year, but in the remaining years of the seven-year cycle they are
                    tithed entirely as demai-produce: Rice, walnuts, sesame, black-eyed peas, [and]
                    there are those who also say early ripening Damascene plums, lo! These are [all]
                    to be treated on the Seventh Year as seventh-year produce, but in the remaining
                    years of the seven-year cycle they are tithed as produce that has certainly been
                    left untithed, and even [had they been brought] from the Upper Rooster and
                    beyond.<lb/>These fruits are tithed as demai-produce in Caesarea: wheat and [if]
                    bread stuffs the dough-portion is always removed, but as for wine and [olive]
                    oil, dates, rice and cumin, lo! These are permitted during the Seventh Year in
                    Caesarea, but on the remaining years of the seven-year cycle they are mended by
                    separating [only] the demai tithe. Now there are some who prohibit [eating]
                    white-petal grape hyacinths that come from the King's Mountain. Unto which place
                    [is it considered] 'within the parameters' of Caesarea? Unto Ṣuwarnah and the
                    Inn of Ṭabitha and [the Inn of] 'Amuda, and Dor and Kefar Saba, and if there is
                    any place purchased by an Israelite, our masters are apprehensive concerning it.
                    Shalom.<lb/>The towns that are permitted in the region of Sebaste [are as
                    follows]: Iḳbin, Kefar Kasdiya, 'Ir, Azeilin, Shafīrīn, 'Ananin, the Upper
                    Bal'am, Mazḥaru, Dothan, Kefar Maya, Shilta, Penṭāḳūmewatha, Libiya,
                    Fardeseliya, Yaṣat, Arbanūrin, Kefar Yehūdit, Mūnarit, and half of Shelāf.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="commentary" ana="b1">
                <p/>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="b1"><ptr target="IIP-071.xml"/>
                        <biblScope unit="page">54-63</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="b2"><ptr target="IIP-107.xml"/><biblScope unit="page"
                            >88-158</biblScope></bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="b3"><ptr target="IIP-155.xml"/><biblScope unit="page"
                            >193-195</biblScope></bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
