<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="evro0014" n="iip">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc><!-- ********** <titleStmt> ********** -->
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Inscriptions of Israel/Palestine</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Prinicipal Investigator</resp>
               <persName xml:id="MS">Michael Satlow</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://cds.library.brown.edu/projects/iip/include_publicationStmt.xml">
               <xi:fallback>
                  <p>ERROR-could not find publication information which should appear in this space.</p>
               </xi:fallback>
            </xi:include>
            <idno type="IIP">evro0014</idno>
            <!--Evro 0014-->
         </publicationStmt>
         <!-- ********* <sourceDesc> ********* -->
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <idno>Evro 0014</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <!-- ********* <msContents> ********* -->
               <msContents>
                  <textLang mainLang="syc"/>
                  <msItem class="#invocation" ana="#christian">
                     <p>Western Galilee. Evron, 415 CE. Mosaic. Invocation.</p>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <!-- ********* <physDesc> ********* -->
               <physDesc><!-- ********* <objectDesc> ********* -->
                  <objectDesc ana="#mosaic">
                     <supportDesc>
                        <support>
                           <dimensions type="surface"/>
                        </support>
                        <condition>
                           <p/>
                        </condition>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <!-- ********* <layoutDesc> ********* -->
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout columns="0" writtenLines="0">
                           <p/>
                        </layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <!-- ********* <handDesc> ********* -->
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote ana="#tessalated"/>
                  </handDesc>
                  <!-- ********* <decoDesc> ********* -->
                  <decoDesc>
                     <decoNote ana="#xx">
                        <ab/>
                        <locus/>
                     </decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <!-- ********* <history> ********* -->
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <date period="http://n2t.net/ark:/99152/p0m63njjcn4" notBefore="0415" notAfter="0415">415 CE</date>
                     <placeName>
                        <region>Galilee</region>
                        <settlement ref="http://pleiades.stoa.org/places/678133">Evron </settlement>
                        <geogName type="site">Church</geogName>
                     </placeName>
                     <p>Found in the northwestern most room of the church complex.</p>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance>
                     <placeName/>
                     <date/>
                  </provenance>
               </history>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <!-- ********* <encodingDesc> ********* -->
      <encodingDesc>
         <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="http://cds.library.brown.edu/projects/iip/include_taxonomies.xml">
            <xi:fallback>
               <p>ERROR: could not find taxonomies file, which should appear in this space.</p>
            </xi:fallback>
         </xi:include>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc/>
      <!-- ********* <revisionDesc> ********* -->
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2011-10-13" who="persons.xml#Kerry_Sonia">Creation</change>
         <change when="2016-12-14" who="persons.xml#Elli_Mylonas">Adding Pleiades IDs to origin/placenames</change>
         <change when="2016-12-14" who="persons.xml#Elli_Mylonas">Adding geo element with lat long coordinates to settlement
         </change>
         <change when="2019-01-29" who="persons.xml#Elli_Mylonas">
                adding period attribute to date element, with Periodo value.
            </change>
         <change when="2019-12-04" who="Gaia Lembi">Corrected encoding (abbreviation)</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface>
         <desc/>
         <graphic url=""/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition" ana="#b1" xml:lang="heb" subtype="transcription" xml:id="evro0014.transcription" corresp="#evro0014.translation">
            <p>יתחיון
                    <lb/>
               <expan><abbr>קלודי</abbr><ex cert="low">וס</ex></expan>
               <lb/>
                    שושן
                    <lb/>
                   מר נאהמ<unclear>נ</unclear>ו
                    <lb/>
                    בסלו 
                </p>
         </div>
         <div type="translation" ana="#b1" xml:id="evro0014.translation" corresp="#evro0014.transcription">
            <p>Let them live - Claudius/a, Susanna, Nehemiah(?), Boselos.</p>
         </div>
      <div type="edition" subtype="transcription_segmented"><p><w xml:id="evro0014-1" xml:lang="syc">יתחיון</w> <w xml:id="evro0014-2" xml:lang="syc"><expan><abbr>קלודי</abbr><ex cert="low">וס</ex></expan></w> <w xml:id="evro0014-3" xml:lang="syc">שושן</w> <w xml:id="evro0014-4" xml:lang="syc">מר</w> <w xml:id="evro0014-5" xml:lang="syc">נאהמ<unclear>נ</unclear>ו</w> <w xml:id="evro0014-6" xml:lang="syc">בסלו</w> </p>
</div>
</body>
      <back>
         <div type="commentary">
            <p>This single Palestinian Syriac inscription was found among thirteen other Greek inscriptions in a Byzantine church in Evron, near Nahariya (evro0001 - evro0013). Two other Palestinian Syriac inscriptions have been discovered in nearby Shelomi and Kabri. These churches, as well as the church at Umm el-Ru'us in Judea, offer some of the earliest known Palestinian Syriac material. The church in Evron was constructed in three stages, the first in the 415 CE, the second between 442 and 443 CE, and the third in 490 CE. The author dates this inscription to 415 CE according to a Greek inscription in the same room. The mosaic is comprised of three main elements: (1) a central Greek cross within a circle, (2) four personal names located above and below this circle, and (3) a dark red tesselated frame. The mosaic is very well-preserved, lacking only one tessera. The circle and cross-bars are composed of white, yellow, and gray tessera. A single large, round green glass tessera appears at the center of the cross. Central white lines of tessera trace the lines of the circle and cross. The six letters of the Syriac phrase "Let them live/be saved" are written clockwise between the four quadrants created by the cross-bars within the circle. Outside of the circle, two names appear above and below this central motif. Above the circle, the name Claudius/Claudia appears adjacent to the outer frame, and the name Susanna appears between Claudius/Claudia and the central circle. Below the circle, the name Nehemiah/Ναυειμαν/Νεεμειων appears adjacent to the outer frame, and the Safaitic name Boselos appears between Nehemiah and the central circle. Concerning the verb written within the circle, the author points out that the appearance of a final nun is odd. He posits that its usage is primarily decorative, attempting to draw the four letters of the circle's upper two quadrants symmetrically. For instance, the round taw and small initial iudh in the first quadrant are similar in appearance to the round waw and final nun in the quadrant to the left. A similar phenomenon occurs in the writing of Susanna, a well-attested Syriac name. The name Claudius/Claudia seems to be an abbreviated version of the Latin name, making the gender unclear. The name adjacent to the lower edge of the frame is less clear than the others. Depending on the reading of a letter as iudh or nun, it can be a either Syriac rendering of the Hebrew name Nehemiah or a Semitic name elsewhere attested in Greek as Ναυειμαν or Νεεμειων. The fourth name is unattested in Western Aramaic but does appear in the Safaitic area with the Greek transcription Βοσελος.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="bibliography">
            <listBibl>
               <bibl xml:id="b1">
                  <ptr type="biblItem" target="IIP-545.xml"/>
                  <biblScope unit="page">47</biblScope>
               </bibl>
            </listBibl>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>